Currier & Ives Darktown Prints
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Currier & Ives Darktown Prints
1880-1907
1880-1896
JWJ MSS 158
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.5
(4 boxes)
Currier & Ives
Cameron, John, approximately 1828-
Worth, Thomas, 1834-1917
Arrangement
Organized into two series: I. Published by Currier & Ives, 1880-1896. II. Restrikes, 1907.
Currier & Ives
Nathaniel Currier and James Merritt Ives, publishers of popular prints in New York between 1857 and 1907. After the firm disbanded, other publishers, including Joseph Koehler in New York and S. Lipschitz in London, acquired the company's lithographic stones and reprinted the images.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Carl Van Vechten, 1965; Gift of Julia Millhiser Gimbel, 1973. Other acquisitions are noted at the folder level.
Scope and Contents
A collection of caricatures of African Americans published by the firm Currier & Ives as a series of "Darktown" comics. The drawings were made by artists associated with the firm, primarily John Cameron (1828-1906) and Thomas Worth (1834-1917). Also present are restrikes of "Darktown" images published later by Joseph Koehler in New York and S. Lipschitz & Son in London.
At the folder level, references are provided to the two standard Currier & Ives catalogues: Currier & Ives: a Catalogue Raisonné (Detroit: Gale Research, 1983) and Currier & Ives Prints: an Illustrated Checklist, by Frederick A. Conningham (New York: Crown Publishers, 1983).
African Americans -- Caricatures and cartoons; Caricatures -- United States -- 19th century; Satires (Visual works) -- United States -- 19th century; Lithographs -- United States -- 19th century; Cameron, John, approximately 1828-; Worth, Thomas, 1834-1917; Currier & Ives; Gimbel, Julia Milhiser, 1902-1983 -- Ownership; Van Vechten, Carl, 1880-1964 -- Ownership; Gimbel, Julia Millhiser, 1902-1983; Van Vechten, Carl, 1880-1964
- Published by Currier & Ives, 1880-1896; Series I
  Arrangement
  Arranged in alphabetical order by title. However, companion or sequel prints were paired and foldered together, thus disrupting a strict alphabetical sequence.
  Scope and Contents
  Series I contains lithographs issued by the Currier & Ives firm.
  The collection combines two groups of prints donated to the library separately by Carl Van Vechten and Julia Millhiser Gimbel, resulting in several instances of duplicate prints in the folders; these are noted at the folder level. Because the prints were hand colored, there are usually differences in coloring, and even variant title fonts in some cases. The donor's name is generally noted on the verso of each print, with Van Vechten's gifts bearing bookplates.
  - The Aesthetic Craze., 1882; 2 copies (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - An Affair of Honor – The Critical Moment., 1884 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - An Affair of Honor – A Stray Shot., 1884 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Asking a Hand., 1887; 2 copies (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Getting a Foot., 1887; 2 copies (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - A Base Hit., 1882 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - De Boss Rooster., 1882 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Brer Thuldy's Statue. Liberty Frightenin de World., 1884 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - De Cake Walk., 1883; 2 copies (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Cavalry Tactics, by the Darktown Horse Guards., 1887 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Infantry Maneuvers, by the Darktown Volunteers., 1887 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - The Champion in Danger., 1882 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - The Champion in Luck., 1882 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - The Champions of the Ball Racket. At the close of the Season., 1885 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - A Change of Base., 1883 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - The Coon Club Hunt. "Hot on the Scent.", 1885 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - The Coon Club Hunt. "Taking a Header.", 1885 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Creating a Sensation. The Bully Boy on a Bicycle., 1881; 2 copies (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Spoiling a Sensation. The Bully Boy on a Bull., 1881; 2 copies (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Crossed by "A Milk Train.", 1885 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Wrecked by a Cow Catcher., 1885 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - The Darktown Banjo Class – All in Tune., 1886 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - The Darktown Banjo Class – Off the Key., 1886 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - The Darktown Bicycle Race – The Start., 1895 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - The Darktown Bicycle Race – A Sudden Halt., 1895 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - The Darktown Bowling Club. Watching for a Strike., 1888 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - The Darktown Bowling Club. Bowled Out., 1888 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - The Darktown Elopement. Hurry Mr. Jonsing..., 1885 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - The Darktown Elopement. Skip softly lub..., 1885 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - The Darktown Fire Brigade – The Last Shake., 1885 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - The Darktown Fire Brigade – Saved!, 1884; 2 copies (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - The Darktown Fire Brigade – To the Rescue!, 1884 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - The Darktown Fire Brigade – Under Full Steam., 1887 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - The Darktown Hook and Ladder Corps. Going to the Front., 1884 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - A Darktown Law Suit – Part Second., 1887 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - A Darktown Lawn Party. A Bully time., 1888 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - A Darktown Opera – The Lovers Leap., 1886; 2 copies (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - A Darktown Opera – The Serenade., 1886; 2 copies (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - The Darktown Riding Class, – The Trot., 1890 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    Custodial History
    Purchased on the James Weldon Johnson Memorial Collection of Negro Arts & Letters Fund.
  - Darktown Sociables, A "Fancy Dress" Hoodoo., 1890; 2 copies (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Darktown Sociables, A "Fancy Dress" Surprise., 1890 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Darktown Society, – On Their Feed., 1890; 2 copies (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Darktown Society, – On Their Manners., 1890; 2 copies (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Darktown Sports – A Grand Spurt., 1885; 2 copies (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Darktown Sports – Winning Easy., 1885; 2 copies (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - The Darktown Tally Ho, – Straightened Out., 1889 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Darktown Tourists – Going Off on Their Blubber., 1886; 2 copies (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Darktown Tourists – Coming Back on Their Dig., 1886; 2 copies (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - A Darktown Tournament, – the First Tilt., 1890 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - A Darktown Tournament, – Close Quarters., 1890 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - A Darktown Trial – the Judge's Charge., 1887 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - A Darktown Trial – the Verdict., 1887 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - A Darktown Wedding – the Send Off., 1892; 2 copies (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - A Darktown Wedding – the Parting Salute., 1892; 2 copies (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - The Darktown Yacht Club – Hard up for a Breeze., 1885 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - The Darktown Yacht Club – On the Winning Tack., 1885 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Darktown Yacht Club – Ladies' Day. In cose I will, Honey., 1896 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Draw Poker – Laying for 'em Sharp., 1886 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Draw Poker – Getting 'em Lively., 1886 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Eating Crow on a Wager. De Fust Brace., 1883 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Eating Crow on a Wager. De Last Lap., 1883 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - A Fair Start., 1884 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - The Result in Doubt., 1884 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - A Foul Tip., 1882 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Going for a Shine., 1889 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Polished Off., 1889 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Grand Football Match – Darktown against Blackville. A Scrimmage., 1888 (Box 3, Folder 43)
    Purchased from Whitlock Farm Books on the James Weldon Johnson Memorial Collection of Negro Arts & Letters Fund, 1974.
  - Great Oyster Eating Match between the Darktown Cormorant and the Blackville Buster. The Start., 1886 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Great Oyster Eating Match between the Darktown Cormorant and the Blackville Buster. The Finish., 1886 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - An Ice Cream Racket – Freezing In., 1888-1889; 2 copies (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - An Ice Cream Racket – Thawing Out., 1889; 2 copies (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Initiation Ceremonies of the Darktown Lodge – Part First., 1887 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Initiation Ceremonies of the Darktown Lodge – Part Second., 1887 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - The Last Hit of the Game. A Home Run., 1886 (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Lawn Tennis at Darktown. A Scientific Player., 1885; 2 copies (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Lawn Tennis at Darktown. A Scientific Stroke., 1885; 2 copies (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - De Lime Kiln Club. A Temperance Racket., 1883 (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - A Line Shot – The Aim., 1881 (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - A Line Shot – The Recoil., 1881 (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - A Literary Debate in the Darktown Club. Settling the Question., 1884-1885; 2 copies (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - A Literary Debate in the Darktown Club. The Question Settled., 1884-1885; 2 copies (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - A Mule Train on an Up Grade., 1881 (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - A Mule Train on a Down Grade., 1881 (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - An Obdurate Mule, – Going Back on the Parson., 1890 (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - A Penitent Mule, – The Parson on Deck., 1890; 2 copies (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - On his Style., 1886 (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - Off his Nut., 1886 (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - Profit and Loss., 1880 (Box 4, Folder 55)
  - Sure of a Bite., 1881 (Box 4, Folder 56)
  - Bustin a Picnic., 1881 (Box 4, Folder 56)
  - A Swell Smoker – Getting the Short End., 1888; 2 copies (Box 4, Folder 57)
  - A Swell Smoker – Giving Long Odds., 1888; 2 copies (Box 4, Folder 57)
  - A Team Fast to the Pole., 1883 (Box 4, Folder 58)
  - Tobogganing on Darktown Hill, – Getting a Hist., 1890; 2 copies (Box 4, Folder 59)
  - Tobogganing on Darktown Hill, – An Untimely Move., 1890; 2 copies (Box 4, Folder 59)
  - De Tug ob War!, 1883 (Box 4, Folder 60)
  - Done Gone Busted!, 1883 (Box 4, Folder 60)
  - Two to Go!, 1882 (Box 4, Folder 61)
  - Got 'em Both!, 1882 (Box 4, Folder 61)
  - Won by a Foot., 1883 (Box 4, Folder 62)
  - "Wound Up.", 1884; 2 copies (Box 4, Folder 63)
  - "Run Down.", 1884; 2 copies (Box 4, Folder 63)
- Restrikes, 1907; Series II
  Organized into two subseries: Published by Joseph Koehler, New York, and Published by S. Lipschitz, London.
  Series II contains eight prints issued by two firms that had acquired Currier & Ives lithographic stones after the company had closed operations. Joseph Koehler in New York published a numbered "Currier & Ives" series, while Lipschitz in London did not credit Currier & Ives.
  - Published by Joseph Koehler, New York
    - The Darktown Fire Brigade – Investigating a Smoke., circa 1907 (Box 4, Folder 64)
    - The Darktown Fire Brigade – A Prize Squirt., circa 1907 (Box 4, Folder 64)
    - The Darktown Fire Brigade – Slightly Demoralized., circa 1907 (Box 4, Folder 64)
    - The Darktown Fire Brigade – Taking a Rest., circa 1907 (Box 4, Folder 64)
  - Published by S. Lipschitz, London
    - "Breaking In." A Black Imp-osition., undated (Box 4, Folder 65)
    - "Breaking Out." A Lively Scrimmage., undated (Box 4, Folder 65)
    - "De Fust Blood.", undated (Box 4, Folder 66)
    - "De Fust Knock-down!", undated (Box 4, Folder 66)